Hi, welcome back to
Nagarjuna, Part Three.
And we've reached Chapter 15,
which is called "An Investigation
of a Nature to Things."
In Tibetan, we can see here,
it's called RANG BZHIN BRTAG PA
RANG BZHIN BRTAG PA
BRTAG PA means PARIKSHA which means...
- [Woman] Investigation.
- An investigation.
RANG BZHIN is an interesting word
because it means "its own face".
BZHIN here means face.
BZHIN RAS which means face.
So RANG BZHIN means
"the face" of something,
which means its nature, which means...
And get it straight at
the beginning, okay?
It means the identity of
something: the inherent nature.
Some quality of a thing
which is inside of it.
So you've got to get this feeling of...
We're going to investigate
whether or not, for example,
fire has an identity or
a nature inside of it
of being hot and then that
nature kind of opens up
and expresses itself in the world.
Does fire have a nature
inside of it which is hot?
And then somehow the fire opens up
and the hotness comes out.
Does it have its own identity?
So when we say nature here,
or svabhāva (svabhava),
RANG BZHIN, think about,
it's sort of a thing deep
down inside of a thing
which is it's true identity.
Think of identity.
All right, here we go to our arguments.
First verse.
First verse and a half.
,RANG BZHIN RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS NI,
,'BYUNG BAR RIGS PA MA YIN NO,
,RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS BYUNG BA YI,
,RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN DU 'GYUR,
If you think about it,
if something's identity is part of it,
it shouldn't have to be created.
If the identity of an
object is inherent to it,
which is what identity means,
it shouldn't be something that you get
only if something else happens.
You're just born with it.
You just come with it.
Nobody has to heat up a fire.
[hands rubbing]
Fire is already hot.
So if it were the case that
you had to do something to make
the fire hot, then hot
wouldn't be the nature of fire.
- Are we agreed? - Yeah.
If you had to do something else,
if you had to light a fire
under a fire to make it hot,
then the nature of the fire,
we wouldn't say hot is
the nature of the fire.
So we can say something
about nature or identity.
It comes with the thing,
and it's not something that comes about
if other things are there,
if other causes and conditions are there.
,RANG BZHIN RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS NI,
,'BYUNG BAR RIGS PA MA YIN NO,
It would be improper to say
that something's self identity,
were only there if
something else happened,
some kinds of causes and conditions.
,RGYU DANG RKYEN LAS GANGS BYUNG BA YI,
,RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN DU 'GYUR,
Because a nature which was
produced by other factors
and other causes would be artificial,
and artificial is the opposite of nature.
It would be put together
and given to the fire.
Oh, here, let me heat you up.
[hands rubbing]
And then the fire gets hot.
Then the nature wouldn't
be the nature in the fire.
It would be produced artificially
and handed to the fire.
Okay, got it?
RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN
So BYAS PA CAN here means
almost artificial, created.
In the jewelry business, they
have real rubies and sapphires
and then they have fake ones.
But when they learned
how to make real ruby
and sapphire in a laboratory,
they had a big debate about
whether to call it artificial or not.
And the guys who succeeded
in the process said
it's not artificial, it's real.
And another guy said it's
not real if you don't
dig it out of the earth.
So they made a compromise and
they called it 'created ruby'.
And it sounds better than
artificial or substitute.
So if it's created, it's not natural.
That's the point.
RANG BZHIN BYAS PA CAN ZHES BYAR
If the self-nature of a thing,
or if the identity of a thing
has to be created from the outside,
JI LTAR BUR NA RUNG BAR 'GYUR
then how the hell can
you call it a nature?
It's artificial, it's created.
Got it?
Like created rubies.
All right.
Nagarjuna...
Now this is a story.
This picture has a story.
So, my lama, I told you I was
a volunteer for my teacher
for 30 years, and about 25 of those years
I was his chauffeur from
New Jersey to Washington DC.
It's a five hour drive.
And he used to teach there once a month.
So I did that drive over 300 times.
I drove him down there.
If you count both ways it's 600.
And so I knew all the road by my
heart and I enjoyed driving him
because he would always
refuse to answer my questions.
And in the car, he couldn't refuse.
He was locked in the car for five hours,
and he ordered the car without a radio,
so I couldn't listen to the radio.
And it costs extra money to
order the car without the radio.
[laughter]
So anyway, all you have to
do is talk about dharma.
Then sometimes he would
pretend to be asleep.
And I'd say I know you're not asleep.
And he...
[imitates snoring]
Anyway, he used to always
stop at a Howard Johnson's
at the Maryland border, Delaware border,
just before the Delaware Bridge.
We'd always stop at the same place,
and he would order his tea.
You know, he's a big tea drinker.
He drank about 15 cups of tea a day.
I made him 15-20 cups of tea a day.
And they would try to give him creamer.
And he'd say, "No, I want cream.
"This is creamer. I don't want creamer.
I want cream. I want the real thing."
And he taught me all these words
for artificial, fake, not natural.
All the words I learned from
him, which were all my words,
they have a context.
We were sitting somewhere and he said,
"This is called BCOS MA."
BCOS MA means BYAS PA.
BYAS PA means it had to be
created from the outside.
It's not natural.
All right.
And he hated this stuff,
dearly.
Okay.
Next verse. It's actually half a verse.
And this is actually RANG LUGS.
So what's that mean?
This is our position.
,RANG BZHIN DAG NI BCOS MIN DANG,
,GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA YIN,
If something was a real identity,
it shouldn't be BCOS MA.
BCOS MA means contrived
or artificially created.
It shouldn't be like the creamer.
It should just be real.
BCOS MIN means not created.
What's a famous BCOS PA in Lam Rim?
BCOS MA?
That's where you try to feel like
a bodhisattva when you're not.
[laughing]
That's a good BCOS MA.
All right. Fake bodhisattva.
Created bodhisattva.
Artificial, you pretend
to be a bodhisattva,
and then you're still messing
up all day, stuff like that.
,GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA YIN,
If something were a true nature,
it shouldn't have to
depend on any conditions
going around outside of it.
If fire is hot by nature,
it shouldn't matter where the fire is
or what's happening with the fire.
It should be hot from the inside.
Something like it.
That's our definition of a nature.
And I was wondering, and maybe
you guys could think it over.
Is this BTAGS PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS PA?
And that's a very, very useful expression.
I remember where I was in a debate one day
in Drepung Monastery.
And I heard this word BTAGS
PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS PA.
BTAGS PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS
PA means theoretical argument.
Theoretical case.
In the theoretical case that
something had a self-nature,
it should have these two qualities. What?
BCOS MIN, it shouldn't
be artificially created,
and it should be GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA
It should not
rely on other conditions.
So can such a nature exist?
That's another debate. Got it?
So in theory, we say in theory, right?
In theory, this is what
a self-nature would be.
You know, in practices, is there
such a thing? We don't know.
And Choney Lama also
expresses his opinion.
And this is a very
traditional ancient opinion
on what a self-nature would
look like if it existed,
and it should have three qualities.
Here we go.
Number one.
GNYUG MA'I NGO BO
GNYUG MA is a very, very, rare,
important word that means
from the beginningless.
[laughing]
GNYUG MA
It sounds like SMYUG MA
meaning a "bamboo shoot", but it's not.
GNYUG MA means primeval,
primordial, since forever.
GNYUG MAGNYUG MA'I NGO BO
If something is the nature of fire,
it should have been in
fires since forever.
Okay?
Meaning hot, heat.
If something is...
If fire has a nature, then a
self-nature or an identity,
then it should have always
been in those things
as long as fires ever were.
That's the first thing.
Fires should have been hot since forever.
Number two.
No matter whether you're talking
about a fire 100 years ago,
or a fire 100 years from now,
or a fire in this room right
now, it should be invariable.
The identity should always be there.
Whether you're talking about
fire 100 years from now,
or a fire a hundred years ago,
or a fire in this present instant,
that identity should always be there.
Hot.
Number three.
It should not be dependent on other
sources for its identity.
And he gives an interesting example.
You don't have to put a
hot water bottle on a fire.
Me and Veronica, we have
this cool thing nowadays
that somebody gave a,
it's cherry pits?
In a bag?
And it has lavender flowers in there,
and you put it in the
microwave and you heat it up,
and then you lie down on it.
It's very pleasant when you go to bed.
It stays warm for like
half an hour or something,
and then it slowly gets cooler,
and you fall asleep on it.
It's very pleasant, so...
That's kind of like a hot water bottle.
So he says,
if fire is hot from the inside
and you don't have to warm up
the fire with a hot water bottle.
It's a bunny with cherry pits
and lavender inside of it.
If you don't need a cherry
pit lavender bunny heat up
in the microwave to make you warm,
you're probably warmed by nature.
Got it?
Those are the three requirements.
Again, it's probably BTAGS
PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS PA
Here's a woman touching a candle flame.
And one thing you can say about the...
One thing you automatically think is
I hope she didn't put her finger in it
because it would burn her.
Its nature is to be hot.
All right, next verse.
This is some kind of other
ideas about identity.
You know, my main thing about
identity is those three ideas.
But let's talk about some other things.
Let's talk about some
other characteristics
of the concept of identity.
,RANG BZHIN YOD PA MA YIN NA,
,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO GA LA YOD,
This is very complex.
If you think about it,
fire has two natures.
One is inherent and one is adventitious.
Its color, for example.
Adventitious means it depends
on outside circumstances.
So which chemical did you...
What chemicals are in the wood
will make a different color of flame.
But the heat is there.
The heat is the identity of fire,
and the color is secondary.
It's a secondary characteristic.
The secondary characteristics of fire
can be created by other forces.
The self-identity or fire
should come from the inside.
So nobody made a fire hot,
but you can change the color
by sprinkling different chemicals in it.
And everything about the fire
is contained in those two things.
Either it's natural identity
or it's a characteristic,
which is imparted by other
circumstances, like its color.
,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO GA LA YOD,
And there's nothing else about a fire.
,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO'I RANG BZHIN NI,
,GZHAN GYI DNGOS PO YIN ZHES BRJOD,
What do you call a nature that
comes from somewhere else?
When the other person thinks of a nature
from somewhere else, we would say
you're talking about a
self-existent somewhere else.
- What do you mean?
- Does the color of the fire
depend on an outside source?
- Yes.
But when you say that,
you think the chemicals made the color.
Got it?
- Is the color of the fire
part of it natural identity?
- No, it can change
according to chemicals.
If you put sprinkled chemicals
on a fire and it changes
the color of the fire,
that's adventitious.
That's, you know, secondary.
That's created by outside forces.
But when you hear me say that,
you think it comes from the
chemicals and that's a problem.
You're even messing up the secondary ones.
Forget that the fire is
hot from its own side
which it's not.
It's hot from your side.
But forget that supposed identity.
You even misunderstand
why it changes color.
You think it's the chemicals.
Got it?
And there's nothing else
about the fire, by the way.
That's all there is.
There's what it is and there's
this stuff it could be.
And you don't understand either one.
,RANG BZHIN DANG NI GZHAN DNGOS DAG,
,MA GTOGS DNGOS PO GA LA YOD,
There's no other fire than the one
which is its natural identity
combined with its other
characteristics that are
created by other forces.
There's no other fire than that.
Once you've covered those
two, that's the whole fire.
And you don't understand either one,
therefore you don't understand the fire.
All right.
,RANG BZHIN DANG NI GZHAN DNGOS DAG,
,YOD NA DNGOS PO 'GRUB PAR 'GYUR,
Anyway.
And here's where he says, you know,
you don't understand the RANG BZHIN
and you don't understand the GZHAN DNGOS.
You don't understand the
basic nature of the fire,
its own self-nature,
and you don't understand
why it's moving or why it has
different colors or stuff,
or why it's different
temperature. You don't understand.
,YOD NA DNGOS PO 'GRUB PAR 'GYUR,
If the identity of the fire
and the characteristics
of the fire existed the
way you think they do,
it couldn't be a fire.
,GAL TE DNGOS PO MA GRUB NA,
If there was no real fire,
,DNGOS MED 'GRUB PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
then you couldn't have
the concept of unreal.
If there's no real fire, then
it's difficult to define unreal.
If there's no real cream
on the table, there's no...
It's difficult for my teacher
to say that's fake cream.
The powder is fake cream.
If he's never seen the
real cream, he can't...
The real cream defines the fake cream,
and the fake cream defines the real cream.
He doesn't smile and say, ah, real cream
if he never had the danger
of having fake cream.
[laughing]
And it was always my
job to talk the waitress
into giving him real cream.
Oh my God, sometimes
that took half an hour.
,DNGOS PO GZHAN DU GYUR PA NI,
When something changes
into something else,
we already talked about it.
When milk, for example,
transforms into yogurt,
,DNGOS MED YIN PAR SKYE BO SMRA,
SKYE BO SMRA means people say,
people in the world say.
SKYE BO SMRA means
Then what did they say?
It's not what it used to be.
When milk changes into yogurt,
how do people talk about the milk?
They say, well, it's
not what it used to be.
Now it's all hunky, and
before it was fluid.
And if you could say about
a thing that it used to be,
then it doesn't have a nature.
That's not what it used to be.
It's not what it used to be means
whatever changed wasn't
inherent, was not its identity.
The milk...
When I look at the yogurt, I say the milk.
It's not milk anymore.
When you say it's not milk anymore,
you're saying something
about the identity of milk.
You're saying that it can end.
You're saying that it
can drop its identity.
Then it's not inherent, is it?
Then it must be coming
from somewhere else, right?
Then it doesn't have an inherent identity.
All it has is these other
characteristics that are created
by outside forces, such as
your your seeds in your mind.
Got it?
Okay.
Then the picture of the real cream.
I always see my teacher smiling
when I look at the real cream.
All right.
Let's go to the next verse.
,GANG DAG RANG BZHIN GZHAN DNGOS DANG,
,DNGOS DANG DNGOS MED NYID LTA BA,
,DE DAG SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA,
,DE NYID MTHONG BA MA YIN NO,
This is this typical...
GANG DAG RANG BZHIN GZHAN DNGOS
Those are the two things:
RANG BZHIN and GZHAN DNGOS.
RANG BZHIN means "its
identity", its natural identity.
GZHAN DNGOS means its "additional
characteristics" added on
by other circumstances.
DANG, DNGOS DANG DNGOS MED NYID LTA BA,
Is it fake or is it real?
Is it real cream or is it creamer?
Is it something made from a
cow that tastes delicious,
or is it something created by powder?
So he's making two sets
of distinctions here:
its identity and its extra
characteristics that are variable;
and then the real milk and the fake milk.
Two sets of differences, two differences.
Two sets of differences.
"When I described them to you,"
Nagarjuna's talking to the other guy,
"you still think they're
all self-existent."
And when I say real or unreal,
and by the way, I'll ask you a question.
Is it true that real can only
be defined by the unreal?
Is it true that identity,
natural identity can only be
defined by characteristics
which come and go?
Is it true that you have to see short
to perceive tall, in Buddhism?
Because there's a lot
of people will tell you,
and I see this all the time,
there's some Burmese school
or something in America.
They're always talking about emptiness
as meaning the result of comparison,
that nothing is real by
itself because it has to be
compared to something else.
Is that emptiness? Is that
dependent origination?
It's not.
It has nothing to do with it.
That whole explanation of
emptiness is ridiculous.
Tall is not defined by short.
Tall is defined by the
seeds for tall in your mind.
That's all.
You're going to have tall without short
because you can have seeds for
tall in your mind without short.
Tall doesn't depend on short.
Tall depends on what you
did yesterday to somebody.
[laughing]
Got it?
Things aren't what they are by comparison.
Real is not defined by artificial.
In Buddhism, in real Buddhism,
an identity is not defined by temporary
coming and going characteristics.
Identity is defined by your seeds.
All right.
,DE DAG SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA,
If you think big is only big by comparison
or identity is only identity
by comparison to adventitious
or coming and going characteristics,
people who say that -- DE DAG
SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA,
,DE NYID MTHONG BA MA YIN
They didn't MTHONG DE NYID -- tattva.
tattva
Yeah, they didn't see emptiness,
DE BZHIN -- suchness.
They didn't see... tattva means suchness,
here.
If you think things are only
what they are by comparison,
in a way, then you're
thinking that identity
comes from its own side
or identity comes from
the side of comparison.
And then you don't understand
the nature of things.
It's a joke. Get it?
You don't understand the nature,
the real nature of things.
DE NYID -- the real nature of things.
It's a joke.
Okay?
By the way, as taught in
the Buddha's teachings,
SANGS RGYAS BSTAN PA LA in the third line,
you don't understand
the Buddhist teachings.
And I don't know.
I got this picture for you guys.
These are three guys with blindfolds on.
And these are the guys who think...
They have wrong ideas about
identity or self-existence,
and they're kind of
wandering around in the dark.
And I just wanted you to see this picture
because I want you to
appreciate why does Nagarjuna
keep saying, "They don't get
it, what the Buddha said."
"They don't get it, what the Buddha said."
Historically, why do you think
he might be hung up on
this point, for $100?
[woman speaking indistinctly]
- Historically, historically.
Why does he keep coming
back to this theme of
"you don't get what the Buddha taught"?
- [Ven.Jigme] Probably
because [indistinct].
- Yeah, good. You got 50 bucks so far.
Jigme said there was another
system that contradicted.
- [Ven. Jigme] It was
popular [indistinct].
- Was popular for how long, for $50?
- [Jigme] 200 years.
- 700 years.
- [Ven. Jigme] Abhidharma.
- Yeah, Abhidharma.
For 700 years, people misunderstood.
They quoted Buddha. They memorized Buddha.
They could memorize.
They could recite all those books.
And according to Nick's
text, Professor Nick's text,
Buddha kept, you know...
the Abhidharma sutras, they
also describe emptiness.
Nagarjuna proves in the 60
Verses that the original sutras
that we call Hinayana also
talked about emptiness.
He proves it.
So imagine how frustrated is Nagarjuna.
He's bucking 700 years
of misunderstanding.
He's trying to stand up in front
of a 700 year tidal wave by himself.
"Hey guys, it's all wrong."
[imitates the wave crushing]
So he has to keep going
back to the scriptures
and saying, "You don't get it.
"You guys just don't get it.
That's not what he meant."
Got it?
Can't you hear 700 years of
frustration in his voice?
All right.
That's in the blind fold. It's
suppose to remind you again.
Now we shift to a major,
major topic in Buddhism,
extremely important.
And I'm sorry it's halfway through
the last class for today
because everyone's tired, but here we go.
,BCOM LDAN DNGOS DANG DNGOS MED PA,
,MKHYEN PAS KA TA YA NA YI,
,GDAM NGAG LAS NI YOD PA DANG,
,MED PA GNYIS KA'ANG DGAG PA MDZAD,
Very, very Nagarjuna.
Very important.
Very important for the two
husbands in the kitchen.
BCOM 'DAS - Bhagavan - the Buddha said
he understood MKHYEN PA.
The Buddha understood
the difference between
DNGOS and DNGOS MED.
DNGOS and DNGOS MED here
means the real and the unreal.
The Buddha understood the difference
between real and unreal.
The husband in the kitchen who is real,
and the husband in the
kitchen who is unreal.
He understood the difference.
And in a book called "Personal
Advices to Katyayana",
this is one of his favorite disciples.
Katyayana.
Katyayana is very important in the sutras
about the Wheel of Life.
He's there when they first
paint the Wheel of Life.
Then he comes home and tells the story.
So anyway, Buddha gave
private advices to Katyayana.
I went looking for them.
You find some, but they're not clear.
LAS NI YOD PA DANG MED PA
GNYIS KA'ANG DGAG PA MDZAD
The Buddha denied that things could exist,
and the Buddha also denied
that things could not exist.
The Buddha denied that things exist,
and he denied that things can't exist.
All right?
And that's really a big Nagarjuna thing.
Very, very important.
It's very helpful in the
two husbands in the kitchen.
For $100. Where's the
deny something exists
and deny that something
doesn't exist, in the kitchen?
You've got to get both to get the $100.
What does exist in the kitchen
and what doesn't exist in the kitchen?
- [Ven.Jigme] The husband you created.
- The husband you created exists.
- [Ven.Jigme] And the
husband you didn't create...
- Yeah, and the husband who's
not your fault, don't exist.
To say that the one that
don't exist, does exist,
is called the extreme of existing.
And to say that the one who
does exist doesn't exist,
it's called the extreme of non-existing.
You went too far.
If the husband in the
kitchen is not my fault,
he don't exist.
Sorry.
If the husband in the
kitchen is not his fault,
he don't exist at all.
Got it?
[woman speaking indistinctly]
And because the husband in the
kitchen is my fault, he does exist.
So the husband exists and
doesn't exist at the same time.
To deny that he exists is a problem.
To deny that the husband who
is your fault exists is wrong.
And to deny that there's any husband
in the kitchen at all is also wrong.
Got it?
Two extremes.
We call it falling off a cliff.
In fact, the picture here
is of a bridge threading ...
I was trying to find one in Arizona.
I got lucky.
This is called Middle Way.
And you're trying to
thread your way through,
doesn't exist and does exist.
If you think the husband who's
not your fault does exist,
you fell off one side.
If you think there's no husband at all,
then you fell off the other side.
And here is the great
reference to that idea
in all of Buddhist scripture.
It's here.
Yay.
Okay.
Which means a good place to
throw in a Sanskrit lesson.
And I researched the
extreme of saying he exists,
from his own side and the extreme
of saying he doesn't exist at all.
So those have special
technical terms in Buddhism,
which is called YOD PA'I
MTHA' and MED PA'I MTHA'
YOD  MTHA' and MED  MTHA'
Say: YOD MTHA' [students repeat]
MED MTHA' [students repeat]
YOD MTHA' [students repeat]
MED MTHA'[students repeat]
YOD PA'I MTHA' means the
extreme of saying he exists...
[Students] from his side,
from his side and not
because I yelled at my kids.
That's called...
By the way, I'm really thinking
the next book I write...
I am going to write
the two husbands sutra.
Okay.
So bhūtah (bhutah), it's
called bhūtahkoṭi (bhutahkoti).
Say 'bhutahkoti'
bhutahkoti, bhutahkoti
'bhutah' means he exists.
'koti' means extreme or cliff.
'koti' means cliff or extreme.
'koti' also means 10 million,
but that's a different thing.
Okay.
So √bhū means to be, and it came from...
in the Indo-European it's called √bheu,
and we get the words be, build.
Where is that Sanskrit lesson?
Oh, I'm sorry. I must have left it out
Oopsie.
Be, build and physics
come from the root √bheu.
Physics also.
The PH in physics comes
from that root √bheu.
'koti' I couldn't find much
except cut, which means
the angle, sharp angle,
something you fall off.
And koṭika (kotika) is the
MU in the MU BZHI MU GSUM,
for $30.
MU BZHI MU GSUM?
[woman speaking indistinctly]
MU BZHI MU GSUM, MU BZHI MU GSUM?
You know MU BZHI MU GSUM.
[woman speaking indistinctly]
- Yeah. What do you call? Permutations.
Four permutations.
So 20 bucks for that answer.
It means four...
It's like you're on a
table with four edges.
Four possible combinations,
Koti, that's called 'kotika'.
All right, good.
Then the opposite is?
What's the opposite,
Christina, of bhutakoti?
Abhūtakoṭi (abhutakoti), abhutakoti.
Which means the extreme of thinking
if he's not coming from his side,
he doesn't exist in the kitchen.
Which is also another extreme.
Which of those two extremes is learned,
and which of those two
extremes is inherent in people?
The classical answer,
so you can chew on it,
is that the extreme of saying
he doesn't exist at all
comes from a bad explanation of emptiness.
That is normally learned.
If he's not what I thought he was,
then he doesn't exist at all,
is most often said by people
who didn't understand
what emptiness means.
All right, here we go.
Let's do some more.
Next verse.
,GAL TE RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD NA,
,DE NI MED NYID MI 'GYUR RO,
,RANG BZHIN GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA NI,
,NAM YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
This is two separate thoughts,
and they are RANG LUGS,
they're our own system.
GAL TE RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD NA
If any entity existed to
some nature of its own,
which means the kind of identity
we've been talking about,
then MED NYID MI 'GYUR RO
-- it could never change.
Okay?
If its identity was inherent,
it could never change to something else,
which means it could never stop,
because that's also changing.
So if things had an identity of their own,
because the identity is permanent,
the thing could never stop
because it had a permanent identity.
It's a very interesting idea.
And he says it would be
like NAM MKHA' MI SGRIB PA
- What's a SGRIB PA, Tim?
Do you remember SGRIB PA?
SGRIB PA, MA SGRIB
To obscure, to cover.
Then he says, Choney Lama says,
NAM MKHA' MI SGRIB PA
- What's that? What's NAM MKHA'?
[woman speaking indistinctly]
- No, not sky.
- [Woman] Space.
- Empty space.
You've got to say empty space.
Four kinds of space.
Never changes.
He says then everything...
If things had identities,
then because the identities
never change, those
things could never change,
because if they changed, they
would lose their identity.
And then that also means if
the identity lasts forever,
the thing would have to last forever.
And it would be like empty
space which lasts forever.
Whether the Earth is in that space,
whether the planet Earth is in that space,
or whether you destroy the planet Earth,
the space is always going to be there.
MA SGRIB means it's open
and cannot be obstructed.
It's not like a box. It's like the space.
,RANG BZHIN GZHAN DU 'GYUR BA NI,
,NAM YANG 'THAD PAR MI 'GYUR RO,
So if the identity of
a thing never changed,
the thing would last forever.
If the identity of thing did change,
then that's not much
of an identity, is it?
If fire could get cold,
then what's the use of having an identity?
Got it?
Then the other guy comes.
And oh my God.
First he puts us, and then
he puts the other guy,
and he doesn't tell us he's switching.
Okay, here we go.
,RANG BZHIN YOD PA MA YIN NA,
,GZHAN DU 'GYUR PA GANG GI YIN,
If the milk's nature could never change,
then where did the yogurt come from?
then who turned into milk?
Who turned into yogurt? Sorry.
If the milk's nature could never change,
then who turned into yogurt?
And then we say,
if the milk could have a
nature, then what changes?
Okay?
It's called RIGS PA MGO MTSHUNGS
RIGS PA MGO MTSHUNGS
means parallel reasoning.
I'll say it again.
He says...
Sorry, I've got to look at it.
If things don't have
a nature of their own,
then how can you say it
changed into something else?
If milk doesn't have a nature,
how can you say the
milk turned into yogurt?
If the milk doesn't
have a certain identity,
how can you say it
changed to something else?
If you don't have a driver's
license to start with,
how can you say you got
a fake driver's license?
How's that? [laughing]
That's the other guy.
And then we say, "No, you don't get it.
If it does have an identity,
then it couldn't change."
Don't tell me it couldn't change
if it didn't have an identity,
which is his argument.
If it's not something, how can it change?
And we say, "No, you don't get it.
If it is something, how can it change?"
[laughing]
Got it? Cute?
Confusing.
Halfway through the second
half, we switched to us.
Thanks, Nagarjuna.
All right.
And I don't know.
I forget why I put a sculptor here.
Yeah.
I mean, the idea is could you change
something which was unchangeable,
or something like that?
All right, here we go.
Don't worry, we're getting there.
The next verse is even more
famous than the last ones
I told you were famous.
This is the super famous verse.
,YOD CES BYA BA RTAG PAR 'DZIN,
Say YOD CES BYA BA [students repeat]
RTAG PAR 'DZIN [students repeat]
MED CES BYA BA [students repeat]
CHAD PAR LTA [students repeat]
DE PHYIR [students repeat]
YOD DANG MED PA LA [students repeat]
MKHAS PAS GNAS PAR [students Repeat]
MI BYA'O [students repeat]
If you think things exist,
you're falling into the extreme
of thinking that things can never change.
If you think that things don't exist,
you're falling into the extreme
that things never started.
Therefore, those of you who are masters
should stay in the middle.
And there's Middle Way.
What's the nickname of Wisdom?
Yeah, Middle Way.
Madhyamika.
That's the nickname of prajna.
Where do you see that
nickname used? For $100.
- [Christina] In the title
of Choney Lama's [indistinct]
- You're close.
- [Tim] Entering the Middle Way.
- Yeah. $100 for Tim.
$100 for Tim.
Yeah.
Chandrakirti did not call
his book Entering Wisdom.
He called it Entering the Middle Way.
But that middle way is
called Madhyamika Shastra,
the commentary on the Middle Way.
All right.
So here it is.
If you think things exist,
then they could never change.
If you think things don't
exist, then you're a nihilist.
Okay.
Therefore, real wise men and women should
stay somewhere between those two.
You should stay between those two.
What's that mean in the kitchen for $300?
- [Pau] To understand that...
- Go slow, go slow.
This is a lot of money.
[everybody laughing]
Where's the Middle Way in the kitchen?
- [Pau] When you understand that
if the husband is yelling at you,
it's because you yelled
at their kids last week.
- Good.
And therefore, that's exists.
What doesn't exist in the kitchen?
- [Pau] The husband that
"because I didn't do anything."
- That "I didn't do anything
husband" doesn't exist, yeah.
So stay between those two places.
Got it?
$300.
[mouth blowing]
She's taking you out to dinner Pachi.
Okay.
[man speaking indistinctly]
Okay, good.
,GANG ZHIG RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA,
,DE NI MED PA MIN PAS RTAG,
,SNGON BYUNG DA LTAR MED CES PA,
,DES NA CHAD PAR THAL BAR 'GYUR.
Okay.
And he expands on the meaning
of unchanging and never starting.
By the way, these two extremes,
unchanging and discontinuing,
these two extremes
are described as the
result of certain opinions.
They're always described as
the result of certain opinions.
If the husband was
coming from his own side,
he could never change -- RTAG PA.
And what's the other one?
CHAD PA
If he, I guess if he is coming,
Oh, if he's not coming from
his own side, he can't exist.
Then he'd just stop.
Got it?
All right.
And I have a special
picture I made for you guys.
The Middle Way to the two husbands.
Okay?
So if you think he's
just from his own side,
you fell off the right side of the bridge.
If you think, if he doesn't
come from his own side,
he can't exist, you fell off
the left side of the bridge.
And if you stay in the middle way,
you have this happy relationship.
Yay!
Oh, I'm so sorry.
That's the last picture in the class.
So let's summarize.
What was the name of this chapter?
We were discussing identity.
Could a thing, could something
have an identity of its own?
And we decided it could not
have an identity of its own
because even those
characteristics of things
like the heat of fire, that
seemed to be in the fire,
are coming from us.
That's the bottom line.
So there is no natural
identity to anything.
Okay.
Oh, what's that mean about
Medicine Buddha mantras?
[woman speaking indistinctly]
Yeah, suppose you had a bad motivation and
you did a Medicine Buddha Mantra?
What would happen then?
That's a sign of the,
of the identity of the mantra.
Does it have an identity
of being beneficial?
No.
If you say those mantras
with a competitive attitude,
then they could hurt somebody, right?
Cool?
That's the emptiness of the mantras.
They don't have an identity of their own.
Cool.
See you next time. Yay!